Well, so, one more
question.  And it's
quite simple.  It's
about confession.
Mhm.
Well, what's the point of confession
?  Because some find that
they are beginning to
confess their,
uh, violations of the
commandments.  But then
they just
keep committing
these minor violations.
And they notice it.
But then it becomes, the
confession becomes so, uh,
just dead.
Mhm.
Because they know, almost
know, or know that there
is a high probability that
next week, in two
week, in two
weeks, I will be
MGM. MGM. MGM.
to succumb
Well, the point is to
offer you
at least, uh, a
small level of
protection if you're
sincere enough.  Because
, uh, sincerity and a
sense of shame go
hand in hand.  So, in the
case of someone who is
sincere enough
to admit, you know, like, well, to
some extent
aware of the weight of
their own actions,
misdeeds, etc., then
adding that
level of confession,
making it public,
can add some weight to
add some weight to
your own unhelpful
behavior, which then
hopefully helps
you not to go down those
paths again.  But
if you are not
sincere enough, if you
have not developed
enough of a sense
of urgency about
the practice, if you
take it for
granted, perhaps
too superficially,
saying, I
will keep the
precepts outwardly,
then my mind
will train itself
.  I will make
confessions externally,
so magically it will
cleanse me of
transgressions and
things like that.  Then
yes, you will get used to what you
confess, and you will
not have a sense of
shame, even if
you confess
it for the millionth time.
So yeah, don't expect
much from this
unless you do the
inside work,
essentially.  That's my
opinion.  But if you
are doing the inner
work, then confession
can give you that
extra layer of
protection.
If you are ready
to open up.
Well, yes, because the discovery would
feel like a
real revelation and
exposure, if you're
honest enough.
Mhm. If you are not
If you are not
sincere enough, then you have nothing to
reveal.  What
you discover is
already seen as
external and
secondary, and you
don't really attach
importance to it.  So
you won't feel
ashamed.  During the
exposure of misconduct.
It will just be like that.
Yeah, it's like, uh, sometimes
if a person
admits to me that
they lied to someone.
Mhm. Mhm.
And I tell them, "Well, you
should confess
to the person you
lied to, not to me or to a
stranger."
Confessing to a stranger,
as I said, can
help if you are
sincere enough, but
even then it is no
substitute for confessing to
the person who
was hurt.
Mm.  Mm.
So yes.
Your immediate
surroundings.
Well, yes, because that's where you
will feel the consequences of
these actions.  Yes.